翻譯：coolguy
校對：樣子@紀錄片之家，hongjinw@紀錄片之家
十一月
It is November.
一輪明月升起
A full moon rises.
約40萬公里之遙的地球彷彿中了魔法一般
Almost 400,000 kilometers away, Planet Earth falls under its spell.
海波微動
Our oceans stir.
正在進行一場古老的海底儀式
An ancient undersea ritual is underway.
這件事的結果
The outcome of this event
不僅影響周圍海水中的海洋生物
will not only affect marine life in the surrounding waters,
而且也會給我們一個關於
but will also give us a clue
整個海洋系統狀況的線索
about the health of the entire ocean system.
主角生物就是珊瑚
The creature responsible is coral.
這是珊瑚的故事
And this is coral's story.
故事伴隨著大量珊瑚產卵
The story begins here,
這一難以置信的場景開始
with the incredible phenomenon that is mass coral spawning.
這是由太陽和月亮控制的年度大事
It's an annual event, cued by the sun and the moon.
它涉及超過140個不同物種
It involves over 140 different species,
並且已經持續了數千年之久
and has been occurring for thousands of years.
儘管珊瑚沒有大腦和眼睛
Although corals have no brain and no eyes,
但單一物種卻能同時繁殖
somehow individual species spawn together,
有時就在幾分鐘之內
sometimes down to the minute.
就像微型情書
Like tiny love-letters,
基因物質混入洋流
the genetic material is cast into the ocean currents,
連接數千公里長的珊瑚礁
connecting reefs over hundreds of kilometers.
像我們一樣，珊瑚花9個月準備繁殖
Like us, corals take up to nine months to prepare for birth.
但很多是雌雄同體，所以它們同時釋放卵子和精子
But many are hermaphrodites, so they gestate both egg and sperm.
在產卵之夜
On spawning night,
它們聚成團塊，並從珊瑚嘴中釋放出來
these are grouped into bundles and delivered through the coral's mouth.
對大多數來說，這是一次無痛的出生
For most, it's a gentle birth.
這一大團很快就分裂開
Over a short time-span, the bundles break apart
卵子和精子必須從其它地方找到它們的另一半
and the egg and sperm must find their counterparts from another colony.
數十億里只有很少能存活下來
Billions set forth, but few survive.
很多其它生物用同樣方法繁殖
Many other creatures choose the same conditions to spawn
礁脈中的水流變成了
and the reef waters are transformed
一個巨大的充滿精子和卵子的液態子宮
into a vast liquid womb, clouded with eggs and sperm.
大規模產卵使潛在的捕食者忙不過來
Mass spawning overwhelms potential predators,
這使珊瑚卵有更多機會受精並佔領一片新天地
so the coral eggs have more chance to be fertilized and begin a new colony.
白天，巨大的光滑海面標記出它們的路線
By daybreak, vast slicks on the surface mark their passage.
珊瑚不僅是水下建築師
Coral is an architect not only of the undersea world,
在水面上也同樣
but above the surface too.
死去的珊瑚掉落沙中
Dead coral breaks down into sand
並最終形成珊瑚礁
that eventually builds up to create coral cays.
這些海岸和淺灘為許多
These shores and shallows provide sanctuary -
別的生物提供庇護所和重要的繁殖地
and important breeding grounds - for a variety of other creatures.
總而言之，數百萬年來，造礁珊瑚
All told, reef-building corals have colonized every tropical ocean,
佔領了每一片熱帶海域，塑造並保護了數千公里的海岸線
shaped and protected thousands of kilometers of coastline
還影響了海洋的演化
and influenced marine evolution for millions of years.
鳥類，比如這些燕鷗
Birds like these noddy terns
依靠珊瑚礁提供食物，珊瑚環島提供棲地
rely on coral reefs for food and coral cays for shelter.
鳥類排泄出種子，使植物在此生長
Birds help vegetate cays by depositing seeds.
這些種子長成樹和森林
These seeds grow into trees and forests
它們反過來又為鳥類提供築巢的場所
which in turn provide the birds with nesting sites.
熱帶海鳥常來光顧這些多沙的邊遠之地
These sandy outposts are frequented by many tropical seabirds,
一些成對的鳥會返回相同的築巢點，年復一年
with some pairs returning to the same nesting sites year after year.
原始珊瑚可追溯到四億五千萬年前
Primitive corals date back over 450 million years.
現代造礁珊瑚則出現在大約兩億五千萬年前
Modern reef-building corals first emerged around 250 million years ago
從此，珊瑚礁為不計其數的
and their reefs have provided homes and sustenance
物種提供家園和食物
for innumerable species ever since.
在珊瑚的漫長歷史中，經歷過五次大滅絕
Over coral's long history, five mass extinctions have come and gone.
每次都有超過90%的生命形態消失
During each, up to 90% of all life-forms perished.
其中的兩次
Two of these extinctions
發生在現代造礁珊瑚崛起時
occurred during the rise of modern reef-building corals.
它們並沒有失去活力，而是存活下來
Rather than falter, they somehow survived,
重塑岸礁
rebuilt their reefs
並再次改變了海洋
and transformed the oceans anew.
現在，珊瑚礁生態系統是許多標誌性
Today, coral reef ecosystems are important nursery grounds
海洋生物的重要繁殖地，如海龜
for many iconic marine animals, such as the sea turtle.
有7種海龜
There are seven species of sea turtle
壽命很長且生長緩慢
and all are long-lived and slow-growing.
它們需要10到30年才能性成熟並在海洋中交配
They take between 10 to 30 years to sexually mature and mate at sea.
這些海洋爬行動物一生中
These marine reptiles are nomadic
要在海洋中遊歷數千公里
and swim thousands of kilometers during their lives.
但強烈的本能和謎一樣的自然力量引導著它們
But strong instinct and mysterious natural forces guide them,
以致當雌龜要產卵時
so that when a female needs to lay her eggs,
會回到它出生的海灘
she returns to the very beach where she was born to do so.
她在沙地上挖洞作為孵化室
Here, she digs a nest and coral sand becomes the womb.
數百隻蛋孵化，卻只有一兩個能長到成年
Hundreds hatch, but only one or two will make it to adulthood.
然後它們可以存活一個世紀
They can then live for up to a century.
如果有只100年前出生的海龜
When a turtle hatched 100 years ago,
它會目睹珊瑚礁的全盛時期
it would have seen the world's coral reefs in all their glory.
工業文明前的海是清澈乾淨的
Pre-industrial seas were clean and clear
數百萬年來，珊瑚擁有良好的生長環境
and corals had enjoyed good conditions for millions of years.
從印度洋到太平洋
Throughout the Indian and Pacific oceans,
從加勒比海到西大西洋
and into the Caribbean and west Atlantic,
珊瑚礁茁壯成長
reefs were thriving.
年輕的海龜遊歷於珊瑚礁之中
The turtle spent its youth exploring these reefs
並見證了珊瑚創造的工程奇跡
and witnessed the engineering marvel that is coral.
通過利用太陽能和完美的回收機制
By harnessing the power of the sun and perfecting recycling,
珊瑚建造了使人類自愧弗如的節能都市
coral built energy-efficient cities that put many of ours to shame.
這些都市聚集在一起成為巨大的帝國
Collectively, these cities created vast empires,
有些從外太空都能看見
some visible from outer space.
在這裡，海龜發現自己有很多夥伴
Here, the turtle found itself in great company,
因為這些海底帝國是許多海洋生物的家園
for these undersea empires were home to vast numbers of marine species
任何形狀，任何體型，只要你想像得到
of every imaginable shape and size
這裡是個熱鬧非凡，五彩繽紛的世界
and were crowded, colorful places.
在眾生態系統中，珊瑚礁是最富生物多樣性的
Today, reefs have one of the highest levels of biodiversity
地方之一
of any ecosystem
也是地球上對生物學研究最重要的地區之一
and are some of the most biologically important places on Earth.
海龜和珊瑚共同目睹了
Together, turtles and corals have witnessed many changes
水下世界的變化
to their watery world.
它們是在6500萬年前發生的
They are some of the only beings
最後一次大滅絕事件中
to have survived the last mass extinction event
倖存下來的生物
65 million years ago.
科學家預測在下個世紀
Scientists predict that in the coming century,
它們將會面臨比上次大滅絕
they will face ocean conditions
更具災難性的海洋環境
as catastrophic as during that last extinction.
精明的老海龜已經看到了警告
Wise old turtles have seen the warning signs for a while.
全世界70%的珊瑚礁已經被毀滅
70% of the world's reefs have already been destroyed
或被嚴重威脅
or are seriously threatened.
七種海龜中有六種
And all but one of the seven sea turtle species
被列為瀕危或非常接近滅絕
are classified 'endangered' or 'critically endangered'.
幾百萬年來第一次
For the first time in millions of years,
海龜和珊瑚的未來變得那麼不確定
the future of both turtle and coral is uncertain.
珊瑚礁的健康狀況受許多因素影響
Many things affect the health of coral reefs,
特別是水溫，海平面高度和海水成分
in particular, sea temperature, sea level and water chemistry.
珊瑚礁可能看起來很堅固，但珊瑚本身很脆弱
Reefs may look mighty, but corals themselves are fragile
它們會因環境的細小變化而受到致命傷害
and can be fatally harmed by just subtle changes in their environment.
當海平面上升過快時，珊瑚生長不夠快
When sea levels rise too rapidly, corals can't grow fast enough
導致珊瑚礁被淹沒
and reefs drown.
由於大氣中二氧化碳含量增加
As atmospheric carbon dioxide levels increase,
海洋酸化加劇，珊瑚礁將會溶解
ocean acidification intensifies and reefs will dissolve.
海水溫度持續升高1-2℃時
And a sustained increase of only 1-2 degrees in ocean temperature
會導致珊瑚白化並死亡
can cause corals to bleach and die.
據預測，全球氣溫將在本世紀末
By the end of this century, it's predicted that the global climate
升高5°C甚至更多
could be 5 degrees Celsius hotter or more.
按照這一速度，珊瑚白化每年都會發生
At this rate, bleaching will become an annual occurrence,
這多姿多彩的美景將最終消逝
and this colorful landscape will literally fade away.
健康的珊瑚礁很容易被看到
A healthy coral reef is easy to spot.
這是個充滿色彩，多樣性和生命活動的複雜結構
A complex structure awash with color, variety and activity.
這個複雜的熱帶花園能與陸地上任何事物匹敵
This is a tangled, tropical garden to rival anything on land.
這花園中最令人驚異的是
Most amazing about this garden
許多「植物」其實是動物
is that many of the 'plants' are actually animals.
像緊握的手掌
Like grasping hands,
珊瑚的嘴貪婪地過濾水流篩選食物
coral mouths hungrily sift the passing currents for food
不分晝夜
day and night.
我們所說的「珊瑚」是一種原始的囊狀水螅
The creature we call 'coral' is a primitive sac-like polyp,
一部分是動物，一部分是植物
part animal, part plant.
動物部分以浮游生物為食
The animal part feeds on plankton.
植物部分由細微的水藻—蟲黃藻—構成
The plant part consists of microscopic algae -
利用陽光進行光合作用
called zooxanthellae - that photosynthesize using sunlight.
每隻水螅都和周圍連成一片
Each polyp is connected to its neighbor,
傳遞能量與營養
passing along energy and nutrients.
它們不斷繁衍創造新領地
These polyps multiply to create colonies,
並結合起來形成珊瑚礁
which combine to form reefs.
通過這種方式，整個生態系統的能量
In this way, energy is produced, shared and recycled
得以生產，分享及循環
throughout the entire ecosystem.
利用它們生產的能量，珊瑚不僅蓬勃發展
With the energy they produce, corals not only thrive
而且製造出用來建造珊瑚礁的
but also manufacture calcium carbonate,
特殊「混凝土」，碳酸鈣
the special 'concrete' that builds reefs.
這是隱藏在珊瑚巨大帝國建築背後的秘密之一
This is one secret behind corals' great empire building.
另一個是無性繁殖
The other is budding.
無性繁殖就是珊瑚蟲複製一個
Budding is a process where coral polyps produce
和自己的基因完全相同的副本
genetically identical copies of themselves
不需要產卵就可拓展它們的領地
and extend their colonies without spawning.
硬珊瑚分泌出碳酸鈣基底
The calcium carbonate foundation secreted by hard corals
有些地方的基底有悠久的歷史
can be one kilometer thick in places
並可能達到一公里厚
and hundreds of thousands of years old.
我們看到的活礁石只是最上面的薄薄一層
The living reef we see today is just a thin veneer on top,
由許多不同的物種構成
made up of many different species,
包括軟珊瑚…
including soft corals...
…扇珊瑚
..fan corals...
…海綿，柳珊瑚和海百合
..and sponges, gorgonians and crinoids.
眾所周知，珊瑚已經進化出1000多種硬珊瑚
All told, coral has evolved into more than 1,000 hard coral species
700多種軟珊瑚
and over 700 soft corals,
每一種都將自己放在合適的地方
each perfectly specialized to fill its own niche.
瞭解珊瑚礁的形成
Understanding how corals build reefs
突顯了氣候變化的嚴重性
highlights the seriousness of climate change
以及它如何威脅這複雜的生態系統
and how it threatens this complex ecosystem.
海洋像巨大的海綿，一直在吸收大氣中的二氧化碳
Our oceans have always absorbed atmospheric CO2 like a giant sponge.
但現在二氧化碳含量過高，導致水中化學成分改變
But now those levels are so high that the water chemistry is changing -
這個過程被稱作「海洋酸化」
a process referred to as 'ocean acidification'.
堿度降低
Alkalinity is falling
自然存在的碳酸根離子受到影響
and naturally-occurring carbonate ions are being affected.
許多海洋生物需要這些離子製造碳酸鈣
Many marine creatures need these ions to produce calcium carbonate
來形成它們的外殼及骨架
for their shells and skeletons.
硬珊瑚需要它們來建造珊瑚礁
Hard corals need them to build reefs.
海洋酸化嚴重威脅到所有這些過程
Ocean acidification seriously threatens all these processes.
但每一個自然災害中，有贏家也有輸家
But in every natural catastrophe, there are winners and losers.
水母是珊瑚的遠親
Jellyfish are distant relatives of coral,
但不像珊瑚，它們更適應
but unlike coral, they are more adaptable
水溫和化學變化
to changes in water temperature and chemistry.
它們的數量還在上升
Their numbers are already on the rise.
讓我們的海水變得蜇人
And they are making our seas sting.
珊瑚的另一個古代表親是海葵
Coral's other ancient cousin is the sea anemone.
與珊瑚一樣
Like coral,
海葵是非常成功的簡單生物
the anemone is a simple being that has been highly successful.
事實上，海葵就像一隻巨大的珊瑚蟲
In fact, the anemone is like a huge coral polyp.
它的中心是一張大嘴
At its center is a mouth
圍繞著一大片帶刺的觸手
surrounded by a vast mantle of stinging tentacles.
它的嘴裡有一個充滿酸性酶的巨大的胃
Within the mouth is a big stomach filled with acidic enzymes.
因為海葵沒有堅實的身體結構或骨架
Because the anemone does not have a solid physical structure or skeleton,
不依賴於碳酸鈣
it does not rely on calcium carbonate,
所以面對海洋酸化，它們不像珊瑚那麼脆弱
so it's not as vulnerable as coral to ocean acidification.
但與珊瑚一樣，變暖的海水會使一些
But, like coral, some species possess zooxanthellae algae
含有蟲黃藻的品種白化
and warming seas will also cause them to bleach.
在800多種海葵中
There are over 800 species of sea anemone.
有10種是適合小丑魚居住的
10 are suitable homes for anemone fish
這是珊瑚礁中最奇妙的夥伴關係之一
and this is one of the reef's most marvelous partnerships.
海葵的觸手通常會刺痛入侵者
The anemone's tentacles normally sting invaders.
但小丑魚身上有保護粘液
But these fish are coated with a protective mucus
使它們可以進進出出而不受傷害
and can dance in and out unharmed.
小丑魚很少閒逛到一米以外
The fish rarely wander more than a meter away.
它們需要的所有東西都在這兒
Everything they need is right here -
食物，保護和集聚群體
scraps of food, protection and community.
沒有什麼可驚奇的
Not surprisingly,
這種魚在海葵保護範圍附近產卵
the fish lay their eggs near the protective folds of the anemone,
供氧並保護它們直至孵化
aerating and defending them until they hatch.
限制在一處並沒有影響它們的性生活
And being stuck in one place hasn't harmed their sex life.
事實上，它們適應了這種生活
In fact, it's enhanced it.
為了讓所有人滿意，它們學會了變性
To keep everyone satisfied, they've mastered sex change.
如果需要雌性家長，雄性變性
If a dominant female is required, a male can change sex.
如果需要雄性家長
If a dominant male is needed,
低級別雄性會加速性成熟
a subordinate male accelerates into sexual maturity.
隨著海洋環境的變化，小丑魚似乎比大多數種類受到更好的保護
As ocean conditions change, anemone fish seem more protected than most,
它們在帶刺武器的懷抱中很安全
safe within those stinging arms.
但是即使它們也不能免受威脅
But even they are not immune from danger.
所有魚類的內部結構和器官
All fish have internal structures and organs
會隨海洋酸化而衰弱
which may be weakened by ocean acidification.
現在，科學家發現
Even now, scientists are finding
魚類的耳骨受到損傷
that the ear bones of fish are being affected,
這影響到它們的溝通方式
which is impacting the way they communicate.
如果海洋酸化不被遏制
If ocean acidification goes unchecked,
它會影響所有海洋動物的代謝過程
it may affect key metabolic processes for all marine animals.
當狀況變得更具挑戰性
Whenever conditions get more challenging,
自然選擇的過程會更加殘酷
the natural process of selection just gets more ruthless.
無法應對的會被迅速淘汰
Those that cannot cope will be quickly cast aside.
每個居民都必須爭取它的生存
Every citizen must earn its keep.
這些蝦集合的地點稱為「清潔場」
These shrimp gather in locations referred to as 'cleaning stations'.
這個特殊的地方恰巧也是海鰻的家
This particular station also happens to be the home of a moray eel.
但小蝦不逃跑
But the shrimp aren't running away.
如果可以的話，它們相互競爭以靠得更近
If anything, they're competing to get closer.
雖然海鰻覺得它們很煩人
And although the eel finds the shrimp irritating,
它也只能苦笑著忍受
he just grins and bears it.
這些完全不同的物種
The reason why these entirely different species
相互容忍的原因是
tolerate one another
它們有個心照不宣的協議
is because they have an unspoken agreement.
蝦需要承擔清除寄生蟲
The shrimp has the important job of removing parasites
和腐肉的重要工作
as well as dying or dead flesh.
這些對海鰻來說是致命的
These can be fatal to the moray,
卻為蝦提供了豐盛大餐
but provide a delicious banquet for the shrimp.
動物們忙於應對珊瑚礁中的複雜關係
Animals are engaged in complex relationships right across the reef.
單打獨鬥是非常冒險的
Going solo is risky business.
如果要嘗試，你最好聰明些
And if you're going to attempt it, you'd better be very clever.
其中一個聰明的生存戰術就是偽裝
One clever survival tactic is camouflage.
裝飾蟹把海綿，珊瑚，海葵附到它的殼上
Decorator crabs attach tiny sponges, corals and anemones to their shells
看上去更像一個行走的花盆
and look more like walking flowerbeds than animals.
其它的試圖通過將有毒海綿放頭上來隱匿
Others attempt to go incognito by placing toxic sponges on their heads,
像這些名副其實的帶帽蟹
like these aptly-named hat-carrying crabs.
海綿是活的生物，但蟹可不在乎
Sponges are living creatures, but the crab doesn't care,
它們把海綿切成合適自己體型的尺寸
cutting the sponge up into whatever size fits.
其他蟹收集海藻葉
Other crabs collect forest leaves
用作偽裝和懸掛式滑翔器
and use them for disguise and as hang-gliders.
拳擊蟹把微小的毒海葵當做拳擊手套
Boxer crabs are always ready for a fight,
隨時準備戰鬥
with tiny poisonous anemones as boxing gloves.
寄居蟹披掛二手外殼來加固自己的防彈衣
Hermit crabs reinforce their own body armor by wearing second-hand shells.
隨著蟹的成長
Bigger shells must be found
它們必須找到更大的外殼
as the crab grows
這讓它們有很多塑造獨特外形的機會
and this gives the crab lots of time to develop its own unique look.
許多老道的寄居蟹尋找帶刺的海葵
More sophisticated hermit crabs collect stinging anemones
換殼的時候把它們弄下來
and will remove these anemones and reattach them
並放到新外殼上
whenever they change shells.
蟹類歷史可追溯到2億年之前的侏羅紀時代
Crabs date back to Jurassic times 200 million years ago
現存種類超過一萬個
and over 10,000 species exist.
它們很頑強，即使少了四條腿也不會使它們慢下來
They're hardy souls - even missing half their legs won't slow them down.
它們還是機會主義者
And they're great opportunists -
有些在海參的嘴裡尋找食物
some feasting inside a sea cucumber's mouth.
海參有些非凡的身體適應性
Sea cucumbers have some remarkable physical adaptations themselves.
它們通過尾部呼吸
They breathe through their rear end,
通過管足利用水壓前進
move on hydraulically-powered tube feet,
海參體壁有一種特殊的膠原蛋白
and have a special collagen in their body wall
使它們能夠迅速改變身體形狀
that enables them to radically change shape.
它們從身體前部產卵
They also spawn from their forehead.
海參很少有天敵
Sea cucumbers have few natural predators.
難怪蝦蟹喜歡把它們當做出租車
So it's no wonder they're a popular taxi ride for crabs and shrimp.
因為海參用身體前端挑起食物
Because the sea cucumber stirs up food with its front end,
蝦蟹甚至能獲得一份免費的食物
there's even a free meal as part of the ticket.
裸腮軟體動物也非常適合搭便車
Nudibranchs are also great to hitchhike.
這些劇毒的海蛞蝓
These highly poisonous sea slugs
在通過危險開闊地時提供安全通道
offer guaranteed safe passage through dangerous open territory,
蝦則在路上負責清潔
with the shrimps scavenging on the run.
但對第一流的旅行來說
But for first-class travel,
沒什麼比得上噴水推進式的水母
nothing compares to a jet-propelled jellyfish.
魔毯在珊瑚上方滑過，以扁蟲的形式
Magic carpets also glide above the reef, in the form of flatworms.
扁蟲和裸腮軟體動物沒有外殼
Flatworms and nudibranchs don't have shells,
所以利用化學戰保護自己
so draw on chemical warfare as defense.
有些吃有毒的水螅和海葵
Some eat toxic hydroids and anemones
並將毒素隔離在皮膚內
and sequester poison in their skin,
這使它們對潛在的獵食者來說具有毒性
which in turn makes them poisonous to any potential predator.
明亮鮮艷的顏色與圖案宣告它們的毒性
They advertise their toxicity with bright, bold colors and patterns,
也使它們美麗非凡
which have conspired to make them incredibly beautiful.
和外貌一樣，它們的性格也同樣狂野
They are as wild in character as they are in appearance.
腮在背上，性器官在兩邊
They have gills on their backs, sex organs on their sides
它們都是雌雄同體
and all of them are hermaphrodites.
還有些是同類相食的
And some are fierce cannibals.
試圖在交配中吃掉你的愛人是難以接受的
Trying to eat your lover during sex is not quite acceptable,
但吃個表親還是可以的
but snacking on a cousin is fine.
海星和海蛞蝓一樣居住在海底
Joining the sea slugs on the ocean's floor are the sea stars.
海星常被稱作「星魚」
Sea stars are often referred to as starfish,
但它們完全不是魚類，它們是棘皮動物
but they're not fish at all, they're echinoderms.
棘皮動物可追溯到5億年前
Echinoderms date back over 500 million years,
比珊瑚的演變早
so predate the evolution of coral.
它們進化出很多生命形式
They have evolved into a wide range of life forms
共同點是棘刺
and what many have in common is the spine.
海膽全身是刺
Urchins are some of the most heavily spined of all,
但對於色彩協調的蝦和蟹，這並不是威脅
but for some color-coordinated crabs and shrimp, this isn't a deterrent.
它們已經適應在刺與刺的間隙生活
They've adapted to live amongst the spines
並一生都在那裡
and remain there all their lives.
這是珊瑚礁中典型的共生案例
It's a classic case of symbiosis on a reef and worlds within worlds.
熱帶海洋就像藍色沙漠，非常缺少營養
Tropical oceans are like vast blue deserts and largely nutrient poor.
在珊瑚礁中，什麼都不能浪費
On coral reefs, nothing goes to waste.
這裡進化出各種專業濾食性動物
Various specialist filter feeders have evolved
篩過流經的水流
to sift the passing currents -
捕捉，消化並回收每一塊食物
capturing, digesting and recycling every available bit of food.
在所有濾食性動物中，蠕蟲是數量和種類最多的
Worms are among the most numerous and diverse of all filter feeders.
現存有2萬個海洋種類
20,000 marine species exist
與陸地上的蠕蟲不同，它們是有毒的束狀物
and, unlike the earth worms, they're an exotic bunch.
就如它們的名字
Befitting their name,
聖誕樹蠕蟲打開它節日羽毛般的口器
Christmas-tree worms unfurl festive, feathery mouth parts,
把它們當做細小的網
which they use like tiny nets.
它們的身體埋在珊瑚礁之中，很少能看見
Their bodies, meanwhile, are buried in the coral and rarely seen.
同樣難得一見的是藍帶鰻
Equally shy are ribbon eels.
它們一生中大部分時間躲在洞穴中
They spend most of their time concealed in deep burrows,
只有頭伸出來
with just their heads peeking out.
它們是海鰻的親戚
They're relatives of moray eels
張開的嘴使它們看起來具有進攻性
and their gaping mouths make them look aggressive.
但它們僅僅在呼吸
But they're simply breathing,
誇張的鼻孔是在嗅找食物
with their exaggerated nostrils sniffing for food.
採用同樣生活方式的是花園鰻
Adopting the same lifestyle are garden eels.
大群纖細的花園鰻從沙中升起
These delicate sea serpents rise from the sand in vast communities,
表演催眠印度蛇舞
performing their hypnotic Indian snake dance.
它們對掠食者保持警惕
Ever watchful for predators,
從經過的水流中緊張地採食浮游生物
they nervously pluck plankton from passing currents,
並用尾巴將自己固定住
their tails anchoring them down.
由於珊瑚的漫長歷史
Because of corals' longevity on our planet,
它們被當做活化石
they're considered our living fossils.
另一個活化石是鸚鵡螺
Another living fossil still with us today is the nautilus.
它是一種古老的軟體動物，當軟體動物最終丟掉外殼
It's an ancient mollusk, whose line eventually dropped its shell...
就帶來了頭足類動物的時代
..and gave rise to the age of the cephalopods.
有珊瑚礁的地方就有頭足動物
Cephalopods are synonymous with the reef
擬態章魚是最有趣的動物之一
and one of the most intriguing is the mimic octopus.
如同它名字中暗示的
As its name implies,
它模仿超過15種動物
the octopus mimics the physical likeness and movements
外表和行動方式
of more than 15 different species,
包括海蛇，獅子魚，鰈魚和鬼蟹
including sea snakes, lionfish, flounder and ghost crabs.
它是自然中最偉大的柔術演員
It's one of nature's great contortionists.
如果它不想被看到，那就肯定不會
If it doesn't want to be seen, it certainly won't be.
許多種章魚都生活在珊瑚礁附近
Many species of octopus live in the vicinity of reefs
真正的珊瑚礁專家是它
and a true reef specialist is this -
晝章魚
the day octopus.
這種章魚是偉大的獵手，魚兒們匆忙保護它們的卵
These octopus are great hunters and fish hurry to defend their eggs.
章魚是如此貪吃
And being so tasty themselves,
這使它們不得不發展出高明的捕獵技巧
octopus have had to develop excellent martial arts skills.
它們有無脊椎動物中最為複雜的大腦
They have the most complex brain of any invertebrate
能同時處理全部八條觸手傳遞的信息
and can process information from all eight arms at once.
它們有短期和長期記憶
They have short as well as long-term memory
並具備通過皮膚進行溝通的特殊方式
and possess a special way to communicate with their skin.
同時高度互動，觸覺性良好
They're also highly interactive and tactile.
求愛儀式可持續數小時
Courtship rituals can last for hours,
一對章魚將16條觸手緊緊抱在一起
with couples intertwining all 16 arms in a sticky embrace.
一旦交配完成，它們將逐漸死去
Once they mate, their bodies are programmed to die.
對某些生物來說，這意味著僅6個月的生命週期
For some species, this means a lifespan of just 6 months.
對其它的，可能長達5年
For others, up to 5 years.
魷魚是章魚的表親
Cousin of the octopus is the squid,
它們謹慎地將卵產在海藻叢中
seen here delicately laying eggs in forest fronds.
我們經常把魷魚稱作槍烏賊
We know squid more commonly as calamari,
儘管魷魚是全世界的美食
but despite being a favored delicacy around the world,
很多品種的數量仍在上升
many species are increasing in number.
像其他頭足綱動物一樣
Like other cephalopods,
它們充分利用海洋掠食者大量消失的機會
they're making the most of oceans depleted of natural predators
而且似乎比別的生物更能適應海水的變化
and seem more resilient than others to changing water conditions.
這個家族的另一個魅力成員是烏賊
Another charismatic member of the family is the cuttlefish.
它們如同具有魔力一般
These creatures have magical attributes.
外部，大眼睛令人印象深刻
On the outside, large eyes as expressive as our own.
內部，三顆心臟推動藍色的血液
On the inside, three hearts that pump blue blood.
在繁殖季，它們三五成群
During their breeding season, they gather in small groups,
小型宇宙飛船般一個接一個急速前進
zooming amongst one another like miniature spaceships.
利用噴水的推進力
Masters of jet propulsion,
它們能向前，後及兩邊隨意移動
they can move backwards, forwards or sideways with equal ease.
它們每年都會回到繁殖地
Every year they return to favorite nesting sites,
比如這個有毒火珊瑚
like this colony of venomous fire coral.
雄性用引人注目的表演和姿勢
Males use dramatic body displays and postures
來競爭交配權
to compete for mating rights.
雖然競爭激烈，但幾乎不用搏鬥
So although competition is intense, it's rarely physical.
雌烏賊從嘴裡取出一團卵
Clutching her brood of eggs in her mouth,
然後把孩子交由珊瑚來照料
a female surrenders her young to the care of coral.
火焰烏賊是名副其實的
The flamboyant cuttlefish is one of the tiniest cephalopods,
最小的頭足綱動物之一
yet lives up to its name.
因骨板太小不能漂浮，所以它更多的是行走而不是游泳
Its cuttlebone is too small to float, so it walks more than swims.
它用閃爍的皮膚斑紋宣告自己毒性很強
And it has a highly poisonous flesh, advertised by its pulsing skin.
它也是致命的掠食者
It's also a deadly predator.
縮在外套膜裡的的兩條專用觸鬚
Two specialized tentacles are contained within a muscular sleeve,
可以像矛一樣迅速發射
which is launched like a spear.
擁有這種捕獵技巧，難怪頭足綱動物
With this kind of hunting prowess, it's no wonder
成功地譜寫了在珊瑚礁的生存故事
the cephalopods have been such a success story on the reef
無疑它們也將會在未來統治海底很多年
and will no doubt rule the seabed for eons to come.
珊瑚礁不僅對常住居民很重要
Reefs are not only important to their permanent residents,
對很多訪客來說也很重要
but also to many oceanic visitors.
常有強烈的洋流以和上升流帶來的豐富食物
Strong currents and rich upwellings of food often occur around reefs
出現在珊瑚礁周圍，這吸引了魟魚等流浪者
and attract nomads such as rays.
事實上，依賴珊瑚礁生存的海洋生物
In fact, the total number of marine creatures dependent on coral reefs
不計其數
is immeasurable.
可能有700萬個物種在生活在這裡
Perhaps as many as seven million species coexist here.
超過4000種熱帶魚與珊瑚礁有關
Over 4,000 species of tropical fish are associated with coral reefs,
其中75%依靠珊瑚礁生存
of which 75% depend on the reef for their survival.
也許它們看起來像是彩色紙片
They may look like just colorful confetti,
但每種魚都有自己的個性
but each fish is its own individual.
魚類有嗅覺，聽覺，視覺和觸覺
Fish can smell, hear, see and touch.
它們能感受到疼痛並且有複雜的關係
They feel pain and have complex relationships.
絕大多數的珊瑚礁魚類都會界定領地
The vast majority of reef fish have defined home ranges.
珊瑚礁供養，收容它們，使它們遠離掠食者
The reef sustains them, houses them and conceals them from predators.
就像被隱形的線拴著的小風箏
Like tiny kites on invisible strings,
魚兒在心愛的珊瑚礁周圍徘徊
the fish hover above their beloved reefs,
只在覓食時冒險出去一下
venturing only far enough to snatch a meal,
除此之外與珊瑚形影不離
but otherwise inseparable.
魚類和珊瑚之間的關係
The connection between fish and coral
是大自然的最持久的愛情故事之一
is one of nature's most enduring love stories.
人類從珊瑚和海洋的
Humans too benefit from a healthy relationship with coral
健康關係中獲益良多
and the seas at large.
珊瑚礁在海中創造障礙物保護海岸線
Reefs create barriers to the sea and protect shorelines.
許多藥物是從珊瑚礁中提煉出的
Various life-saving medicines are extracted from reefs.
海洋的衍生化學品被用來治療許多疾病
Ocean-derived chemicals are used to treat many illnesses,
包括癌癥
including cancer.
微小的海藻處理大氣中的二氧化碳
Microscopic marine algae processes our atmospheric CO2
並產生70%的氧氣
and produces 70% of the oxygen we breathe.
因此，像這些魚一樣，我們的生存需要健康的海洋
So, like these fish, we need healthy oceans to survive
還需要健康的珊瑚礁保護家園
and reefs to secure our homes.
不論在陸地上還是海底
In both our terrestrial world and the undersea,
創造與毀滅總是在不斷地循環
there have been constant cycles of creation and destruction.
大自然的規則就是混亂
The rule of nature is chaos.
儘管珊瑚礁看上去很和諧
Although a reef looks harmonious,
它和其它生態系統一樣混亂
it's as chaotic as any other ecosystem.
其中一種在混亂中生存的方法就是
And one of the ways to survive chaos,
不論你在海面上還是海面下
whether you're above or below the surface,
都要和別人合作
is to cooperate.
這種合作叫做共生
This cooperation is called symbiosis,
是一種存在於兩種
a mutually beneficial relationship
不同物種間的互惠關係
between two entirely different species.
如果不能把自己變得有用的話
These little blue and black striped wrasse would be perfect fish food
這種藍黑相間的小瀨魚將是完美的魚食
if they hadn't made themselves so useful.
它們是靠清潔工作賺取來贏得生存的裂唇魚
They're cleaner wrasse and earn their keep by cleaning.
這項服務如此重要
So vital is this service
以致於感激的主人從不敢吃掉它們
that none of their grateful hosts would ever dare to eat them.
當雙方都獲利時，平衡關係隨即建立
Both parties benefit and a form of balance is achieved.
珊瑚礁中有種穩定的張力
There is constant tension on the reef
因為不同的物種在平衡中活動
as different species work out this balance
並努力延長它們在歷史中逗留的時間
and try to maximize their moment in history.
對某些大魚來說
For some of the bigger fish,
那段時間常被延伸到數十年
that moment used to stretch into decades.
有些甚至有一個世紀或更多
Some even lived for a century or more.
但是高齡者日益少見
But old age is a rarity now
標誌性的珊瑚礁物種就在我們眼前消失
and iconic reef species are vanishing even as we watch.
野生神僊魚的壽命有10到15年
Angelfish live for 10 to 15 years in the wild
是珊瑚礁中最可辨的生物之一
and are some of the reef's most recognizable species.
它們被收藏者視若珍寶
They are highly prized by collectors
但不幸的是，很多只能在水族館度過漫長的一生
and, tragically, many live out their long lives in aquaria.
池中的魚就像籠中的鳥
A fish in a tank is like a bird in a cage -
我們可以觀察它們，卻對其野生狀況知之甚少
we're able to observe them but we get little idea of their wildness.
只有在這裡，珊瑚礁中
It's only here, on the reef,
我們才能真正體會魚類的生活有多麼複雜
that we can truly appreciate just how complex a fish's life can be.
有的神僊魚沒有固定伴侶
Some angelfish are promiscuous,
有的因生活所需結合在一起
some bond for life,
有的則是一夫多妻
others have male-driven harems.
許多魚類，包括這種纖美的三棘高身鲉
And many fish, including these delicate leafed scorpionfish,
忙於進行長時間的求偶儀式
engage in long courtship rituals.
每週都會發現新的魚類
New species of fish are discovered every week,
每一個發現都成為新信息的財富
and with each discovery comes a wealth of new information.
有的每天產卵
Some spawn daily,
其它的直到20或30歲才開始繁殖
others do not begin breeding until they are 20 or 30 years old.
許多生命開始時是雄性，結束時卻是雌性
Many start life as a male but die a female.
大多數具有高度社會性
Most are highly social
其智力超過我們的理解
and have intelligence beyond our comprehension.
翻譯：coolguy
校對：樣子@紀錄片之家，hongjinw@紀錄片之家
像在非洲平原上的牛羚和斑馬
Like wildebeest and zebra on the African plains,
刺尾魚和鸚嘴魚一起吃草
tangs and parrotfish often graze together.
它們都是食草動物
Both fish are herbivores
以藻類甚至活珊瑚為食
and dine on algae and even live coral.
其它種類則聚集在珊瑚礁頂部
Other species converge on the reef crest.
這裡暴露在波浪和陽光下
This area is exposed to wave action and lots of sunlight
有豐富的營養
and is rich in nutrients.
花尾連鰭魚會搬動石塊
Fish like this rock-mover wrasse
來尋找蠕蟲和軟體動物
literally move rocks in the search of worms and mollusks.
這樣的覓食很辛苦
Dining this way is hard work,
所以它們並不總是願意分享覓食地
and they're not always willing to share their patch.
其它魚類挖掘基底併吞下一大口沙子
Others excavate the substrate and swallow large mouthfuls of sand.
它們的身體是為過濾沙中的海藻
Their bodies are specially designed to filter the sand for algae,
並通過腮排除廢物而專門設計的
dispelling waste through their gills.
不是什麼時候都能去珊瑚礁頂部
Access to the reef crest is limited.
只有漲潮並風平浪靜時
It's only at certain tides and during calm seas
才可能在那裡覓食
that it's possible to feed here.
萬事俱備
When all the conditions are right,
魚兒從幾英里外游來抓住這個難得的機會
fish arrive from miles around to take advantage of this rare opportunity.
有的成雙成對，有的獨來獨往
Some are in couples, others dine alone,
完全不同的生物一起覓食
and completely different species feed side by side.
這是生物多樣性的最佳狀態
It's biodiversity at its best.
古怪的泥土搬運工，比如鲀魚
Eccentric earth-movers, like triggerfish,
也加入到晚宴中
also join the dinner party.
它們會用強有力的喙
They use their powerful beaks to cast aside whole chunks of coral,
拋開整塊珊瑚
as they search for clams,
尋找蛤蜊，蝦和蟹
shrimp and crabs.
它們已經無暇顧及餐桌禮儀了
They're much too busy to worry about their table manners.
像人類的城市
Like a human city,
珊瑚礁作為調和混亂的角色
a reef boasts an eclectic jumble of characters
不同生物各有自己的生活選擇
conducting themselves in a variety of ways.
有獨行俠，流浪者
There are loners and drifters.
有的進行秘密集會
There are clandestine meetings
地下活動
and underground movements.
有的小心機警
There are the watchful and the wary.
各種方式的自我表現
And different forms of self-expression.
就像在城市中一樣，有奇怪的聯盟出現
As in all of our cities, strange alliances occur...
古怪的時尚也可容忍
..and odd fashion is tolerated.
無論美醜都有一席之地
Every beauty and beast has its place.
珊瑚礁和陸地一樣，24小時為一週期
Just like the terrestrial world, a reef has a 24-hour cycle.
當下午的陽光開始黯淡
As the afternoon light begins to fade,
這些軟魚產卵後便馬上離開
fish, like these anthias, spawn with abandon,
它們知道夜晚即將到來
knowing that night will soon follow
並利用夜色保護魚卵
and conceal their eggs.
這時，小魚抖動身體
Meanwhile, tiny fish shudder their bodies,
表明它們做好了交配的準備
indicating their readiness to mate.
無數的晝行魚被蒼茫的暮色刺激
And countless other daytime fish are inspired by the waning light
開始獻慇勤或繁殖
to court or breed.
一對管口魚跳著誘人的劍舞
Here, a pair of flutemouths engage in a seductive sword dance.
這是管口魚式的「前戲」
It's their form of foreplay,
並且已經持續了好幾小時
and they've been at it for hours.
幾千年來，獵人與獵物間的戰爭
Over the millennia, the battle between predator and prey
為海底生物的「軍備競賽」推波助瀾
has fueled an evolutionary arms race under the sea.
大自然總是將她的設計升級
Mother Nature is always updating her designs
並淘汰過時的那個
and making old ones redundant.
動物們必須不斷提高
Animals have had to constantly refine
它們的進攻和防禦能力
their offensive and defensive capabilities.
結果可能像科幻小說
The result can be pure science fiction.
安康魚和蝎子魚的模樣非常怪異
Angler and scorpion fish are as bizarre as they come.
它們是海綿的專業模仿者
They're expert mimics of sponges,
但有世界上最快速的一擊
but have one of the fastest strikes on Earth.
不過它們肯定贏不了選美比賽
But they're certainly not out to win a beauty prize.
當它碰到同類時，愛是盲目的
When it comes to some of these creations, love is certainly blind.
從人類歷史開始時，我們就對這無數生命著迷不已
This myriad life has enthralled us since the beginning of human history.
我們起源於海洋
We did originally evolve from the sea.
自從早期人類首次出現
And ever since early humans first emerged,
我們就被拉回到海岸邊
we've been drawn back to its shores.
海鮮是受人青睞的食物
Seafood has been a favored diet.
貝殼成為貨幣和寶石
Shells have been our money and jewelry.
珊瑚石灰岩鋪平道路
Coral limestone paves our roads.
沙子築成房屋
Sand cements our houses.
我們的神話和傳說，書籍與影片
Our myths and legends, books and films
充滿了源自海洋的角色
are all full of characters derived from the sea.
當光線黯淡，主角開始變換
And as light fades, these characters begin to change
珊瑚礁的故事變得大為不同
and the story of coral moves into a very different narrative.
大型掠食性魚類巡遊在珊瑚礁邊緣，尋找致命一擊
Big predatory fish cruise the reef's edge, searching for a final kill.
晝行魚匆忙躲藏
Daytime fish hurry into hiding.
這是個危險的過渡時間
This is a dangerous time of transition.
整個珊瑚礁裡開始換崗
All across the reef, there is a changing of the guard.
夜班開始了
The night shift has begun.
人類對海洋知之甚少
Little is known about our oceans.
火星地表都被更精確地繪製過
The surface of Mars is better mapped.
大多數活珊瑚在水下淺於50米的地方
Most living coral reefs descend to only 50 meters or so,
那是由於對陽光的依賴
due to the reliance on sunlight.
但有些地方海床下降到11000米
But the seafloor falls to 11 kilometers in places.
這就是我們所說的「深淵」
This is what we call the abyss.
夜幕下的珊瑚礁使我們感覺到
Night-time on the reef gives us a sense
深淵中可能的樣子
of what this abyss might be like.
漆黑的一片富有活力，滿是奇異生物
The inky black is very much alive and full of aliens.
在長有深海珊瑚的特殊地點
In special places where reefs drop to great depth,
深海浮游生物上升到水面
deep sea plankton rise to the surface
捕食淺水浮游植物
to hunt shallow water phytoplankton.
它們游經數百米
They travel hundreds of meters.
數以億計
They number in their billions
每晚重複旅程
and they repeat the journey every night.
這是動物王國裡最壯觀的遷徙之一
It's one of the biggest migrations in the animal kingdom.
浮游生物獵人和獵物間的追逐
The chase of plankton-hunter and plankton-prey
引發了晚間珊瑚礁中更大的反應鏈
triggers a larger chain reaction right across the night-time reef.
籃海星從巢穴中出來
Baitfish snatch mouthfuls,
伸出網狀觸角
while basking stars emerge from their lairs
餌魚藉機大口搶食
and extend web-like arms.
當浮游生物瘋狂地相互溝通時
The water flashes with color
海水閃爍著五彩顏色
as the plankton frantically communicate with one another.
珊瑚並不是無所事事的旁觀者
Coral is not an idle bystander.
珊瑚礁已成為一堵滿是嘴巴的牆
The reef has become a wall of mouths.
珊瑚真正的動物本性顯示出來
The true animal nature of coral is revealed.
配備有毒刺和酸液的珊瑚蟲
Equipped with poisonous harpoons and acid,
每一隻都是一個無法逃脫的致命陷阱
each polyp becomes a deadly trap from which escape is impossible.
鯰魚在行進中進食
Meanwhile, catfish eat on the run.
鸚嘴魚睡覺時把眼睛睜得大大的
Parrotfish sleep with eyes wide open
或是隱藏在薄粘液膜中
or conceal themselves in mucus cocoons.
沒有手電筒的話，人類無法在夜間視物
Without torches, humans are blind at night.
在水下，我們幾乎不能辨別方位
Underwater, we'd barely know up from down.
但水下獵手卻沒有一點不便
But the undersea hunters are not at all disadvantaged.
它們用震動，電子脈衝和化學物質
Instead of sight, they use vibration, electrical impulses
代替視覺，來追蹤獵物
and chemical traces to find what they're after.
石頭牆，其實是石頭魚在等待伏擊
Stone walls are, in fact, living stonefish waiting in ambush...
長有利齒的鰧魚潛伏在淤泥中
..while the sharp teeth of stargazers lurk beneath the muck.
獵物很容易在不知情時游向危險
It's easy to swim towards danger without realizing it.
這只海葵已成為連環殺手
This anemone has become a serial killer.
一隻幸運的烏賊逃走了，並釋放墨水掩蓋其蹤跡
A lucky squid escapes, releasing ink to cover its tracks.
海龍看著魚兒四散
A pipefish looks on,
並有更多淪為受害者
as fish scatter and more fall victim.
下降到海床上
Down on the seabed,
食腐動物收集殘羹剩飯
scavengers collect the scraps...
獅子魚用長刺捕捉毫無戒心的獵物
..while lionfish use their long spines to herd unsuspecting prey.
所有地方都有生命活動
There is activity in all directions,
形形色色的夜間獵人吃飽了
as night hunters of every description eat their fill.
躄魚回來了，適得其所
The anglerfish is back and now completely in its element.
也許它的動作算不上優雅
It may not move with grace,
但那對捕食沒什麼影響
but that doesn't affect its chances for a kill.
它所需要的只是等待食物游進自己的嘴裡
All it needs to do is wait for a meal to come to its mouth.
說到夜間狩獵
When it comes to nocturnal hunting,
海鱔因其邪惡外表而聞名
moray eels are known for their viciousness.
但其它獵手就不那麼容易認出了
But other killers are not so easy to spot.
蝦蛄老練又野蠻
Mantis shrimp are sophisticated and savage.
它們擁有極佳視力
They're armed with supreme eyesight
積極捕食獵物
and actively hunt live prey
其它甲殼動物，比如龍蝦
while other crustaceans, like lobsters,
則在海底尋找剩菜
scour the sea floor for leftovers.
由於之前的繁忙時光
With a busy time ahead,
儘管周圍有這麼多的活動，晝行魚仍試著睡覺
day fish try to sleep despite all the activity.
有些好像飄在黑暗中的幽靈
Some drifting like ghosts in the dark.
小丑魚也試著睡覺，但並不容易
The anemone fish are also trying to sleep, but aren't finding it easy.
它們的扁平夥伴，斑點蟹，正在享受宵夜
Their flat-mates, the dotted crabs, are enjoying a midnight snack.
最活躍的夜間徘徊者是貝殼
Some of the most active night prowlers are shells.
大多數人只能從貝殼店或沙灘上的死貝殼瞭解它們
Many of us only know them from shell shops or dead on the beach.
但活貝殼更珍貴
But shells alive are much more precious -
它們好像吉普賽大篷車，在不斷地移動中被海水擦亮
gypsy caravans, varnished by the oceans, constantly on the move.
黑暗也適合求愛的花斑連鰭銜魚
Darkness also suits courting mandarin fish.
它們有很強的性衝動
They have an unusually high sex drive
如果需要的話，它們每晚都可以產卵
and can spawn every night if the urge takes them.
儘管水下的燈光可讓我們匆忙一瞥
Although our underwater lights give us a glimpse,
我們仍然對珊瑚礁的夜間活動知之甚少
we still know very little about what happens on a reef at night.
而我們那種無理由的恐懼使之更加難以被瞭解
And our unwarranted fears have made it harder to learn.
我們對海洋的態度一直充滿矛盾
Our attitude to the sea has been full of contradiction.
一方面我們尊敬它
On the one hand we've revered it,
另一方面我們將它視為敵人
on the other we've seen it as an enemy -
黑暗，深不可測，滿是怪獸
dark and unfathomable, full of dragons and monsters.
深海怪獸早就
These monsters of the deep
被證實是我們虛構的
have long been proven figments of our collective imagination.
但有些人相信它們仍然以鯊魚的形式存在
But some believe they still exist in the form of sharks.
真是天大的錯誤
How wrong they are.
這些神奇的生物比恐龍出現得還早
These magnificent creatures predate dinosaurs.
和珊瑚一樣，它們在幾次大滅絕中倖存
Like coral, they've survived several mass extinctions
並在塑造海洋進化的過程中扮演了同等重要的角色
and have played an equally vital role in shaping ocean evolution.
鯊魚已在海洋中漫遊了超過4億年
Sharks have been roaming our seas for over 400 million years.
化石記錄顯示千萬個物種出現並消亡
Fossil records show that thousands of species have come and gone,
但其中370種還和我們在一起
of which 370 are with us today.
它們在世界各地都能找到
They can be found worldwide,
有許多依賴於珊瑚礁生態系統，以獲得保護和食物
with many dependent on coral reef ecosystems for protection and food.
作為頂級掠食者
As top predators,
鯊魚影響了整個食物鏈的
sharks have influenced adaptation and evolution
適應性和進化
all the way down the food chain.
但是，與傳統認識相反
But, contrary to popular myth,
鯊魚不僅僅是依靠本能的捕食機器
sharks are not just instinctive eating machines.
許多種鯊魚展示了強大的解決問題的能力
Many species exhibit powerful problem-solving skills
它們的腦和體重比與其它更高級的脊椎動物
and their brain-to-body-mass ratio is similar to many mammals
及許多哺乳動物相似
and other higher order vertebrates.
所以它們聰明，好奇，好交際
So they are as intelligent, curious and social
和某些我們更喜歡的動物一樣
as some of our more favored animals.
它們不僅擁有我們具有的5種感覺
They not only possess the 5 senses we do -
視覺，聽覺，觸覺，嗅覺，味覺
sight, hearing, touch, smell and taste -
還能感知電流
but can also perceive electrical currents
和磁場
and magnetic fields.
如果我們和它們在水下
If we're in the water with them,
它們在幾英里外就能感知到我們的存在
they can detect our presence from miles away.
它們能監測到我們的心跳
They can monitor the beating of our heart...
還能讀懂我們的情緒
..and read our mood.
涉及到人類時，它們通常是謹慎的生物
When it comes to humans, they are normally cautious creatures.
只要有可能，它們會避開我們
Whenever possible, they avoid us.
原因很明顯
With good reason.
每年超過1億條鯊魚被殺
Every year, over 100 million sharks are killed,
這主要是為了它們的鰭
the majority just for their fins.
魚翅是亞洲湯的傳統配菜
Their fins are a traditional ingredient in Asian soup
其價值相當於魚子醬
and their value rivals caviar.
鯊魚被割去魚鰭時還活著
The sharks are often finned alive
被扔回海裡後才溺死
and thrown back into the water to drown.
由於過度捕撈
One third of all open-ocean shark species are now facing extinction,
所有公海鯊魚中，有1/3的種類已瀕臨滅絕
primarily due to over-fishing.
如果說海洋裡有殺戮機器的話，不是它們
So if there is a killing machine in our seas, it's not them,
而是我們
it's us.
所以鯊魚都受到威脅
No shark is safe,
即使是最大的鯊魚，鯨鯊
not even the biggest of them all, the whale shark.
長達15米，重達12噸，它們令人印象深刻
Up to 15 meters long and 12 tons in weight, they're an impressive sight.
它們是嚴格的濾食性動物，主要以浮游生物為食
But they're strictly filter feeders and dine mostly on plankton.
令人難以置信的是，它們也是非法捕魚的受害者
Unbelievably, they are also victims of illegal fishing.
鯨鯊不是鯨而是鯊魚
Whale sharks are not actually whales but sharks.
小須鯨才是遊歷在珊瑚礁中的真正的鯨魚
True whales that visit the reefs include these, the minke.
但這些優雅的動物竟然也被人類捕殺
Incredibly, these graceful animals are still being harpooned.
無論如何，它們是那樣信任我們
What trust they show us, regardless.
在我們開始掠奪海洋之前，它們是這個樣子
Before we began to plunder the seas, this is what they were like.
連接著深淵與海面
Linking the abyss with the surface,
層層疊疊，銀光閃閃
layer upon layer of shimmering silver.
大型魚群是健康海洋的標誌形象
A big school of fish is a defining image of a healthy sea.
這是力量和驚人適應性的展示
It's a show of strength and incredible physiological adaptation.
大多數魚從頭部到尾部
Running head to tail in most fish
有一排魚鱗叫做側線
is a row of scales known as the lateral line.
這條連接到腦神經的線
Connected to nerves in the brain,
包含有特殊的細胞
this line consists of specialized cells
對水的位移及運動很敏感
that are sensitive to water displacement and movement.
同時，魚眼長在頭部兩側
Meanwhile, fishes' eyes are located on the sides of their heads
使它容易看清自己同其它魚的位置關係
to make it easy to see where they are in relation to one another.
所以，視力有助於保持魚兒之間的角度和距離
So, vision helps maintain angle and distance between fish,
側線則決定了整個魚群的速度和方向
while the lateral line dictates speed and direction of the entire school.
這樣，許多魚可以作為整體來行動
In this way, many fish can move as one
跳著它們自創的水下芭蕾
and choreograph their own aquatic ballet.
許多魚群是由幼魚組成
Many fish school as juveniles
有約一半以上種類的魚都會在
and around half of all fish species form aggregations
生命中的某段時間聚集成群
at some point in their lifecycle.
就算是喜歡獨行的魚也會時不時的加入魚群
Even fish that prefer their solitude join a school from time to time.
梭魚在晚上獨自獵食
Barracuda hunt on their own at night
但白天成群結伴以獲得保護
but hang out in packs during the day for protection and company.
它們有尖尖的頭和流線型的身體
With their pointed heads and streamlined bodies -
可以長到2米長
up to 2 meters long -
它們像箭一樣一起穿越大海
they fly in unison through the blue like polished arrows.
群聚使得掠食者很難專注於一個目標
Schooling makes it hard for a predator to focus on one target
這是很好的防禦機制
and is a great defense mechanism.
進食時，這也是一股不容忽視的力量
It's also a force to be reckoned with when it comes to feeding.
少有浮游生物能逃脫張開的嘴的掃蕩
Few plankton in the area will escape this sweep of open mouths,
比如這些罕見的濾食性鯖魚施展的協同攻擊
as these rare filter-feeding mackerel make their coordinated attack.
億萬年來，群聚行為曾在許多方面幫助魚類
Over the eons, the art of schooling has helped fish in many ways.
但是現在，諷刺的是，它導致了魚類的沒落
But now, ironically, it contributes to their downfall.
下一次網就能捕捉到一噸魚
Just one net can collect a ton of fish at once.
每年超過1億噸海魚被捕撈
And over 100 million tons of fish are hauled from the oceans each year.
大魚群所剩無幾
For the few big schools left,
穿過空曠的大海時，它們肯定感覺很怪異
it must feel quite eerie moving through so much empty liquid blue.
今天，對魚群來說安全的地方
These days, one of the only safe places for schooling fish
只剩海洋保護區了
is a marine sanctuary.
自從建立保護區以來
Whenever sanctuaries have been established and policed,
魚類數量緩慢增長
fish stocks have slowly increased,
這有助於恢復生物多樣性
helping to restore biodiversity.
成功的保護區成為寶貴的時光膠囊
A successful sanctuary becomes a precious time capsule...
提醒我們海洋曾經是多麼富饒
..a reminder of how rich the seas once were.
而且能再次變得富饒
And could be again.
和動物園不一樣，海洋保護區沒有圍牆
Unlike a zoo, a marine sanctuary has no walls.
所以它不僅有能力恢復鄰近區域
So it has the capacity to not only replenish the immediate area,
還能恢復周圍的海域
but the oceans around it.
我們給自己的海域起了不同的名字
Because we have individual names for our oceans
還有領土邊界
and have territorial borders,
但我們忘記了只有一個生態系統
we forget that there's only one system.
只有一個海洋
There is only one sea.
海水，覆蓋地球表面的70%，連接著所有生靈
Water, covering 70% of our planet's surface, connects us all.
即使在極地發生的事也會影響到珊瑚
What occurs even in our polar regions will eventually affect coral.
相反，每一個新的海洋保護區都是
And, conversely, each new marine sanctuary is another powerful step
拯救海洋的有力步伐
towards saving our seas.
當你意識到
And when you consider
海洋構成了地球上99%的生物圈
that the global ocean makes up 99% of the living biosphere of the planet,
那麼每一步都很有意義
every step counts.
由於對許多海洋生物來說
Because reefs are such important breeding grounds
珊瑚礁是非常重要的繁殖地
for so many marine creatures,
這可能是全新未來的起點
this is where a new future might lie.
復甦是個日常事務
Renewal here is a daily affair
並帶來神奇的轉變
and brings with it magical transformation.
這裡，石斑魚求愛時，身體顏色變紅
Here, a coral cod blushes a different color when wooed by its mate.
蓬勃的珊瑚礁就像水中的彩虹
A thriving reef is an aquatic rainbow.
就像石斑魚的皮膚
And like the skin of the coral cod,
這些顏色自有其意義與功能
these colors have meaning and function.
銀色的鱗片反射光線
Silver scales reflect light
使魚兒和水中背景融為一體
and allow fish to blend into their watery backgrounds.
大膽，強烈的顏色使魚兒在魚群中
Bold, strong colors allow fish to recognize their own species
辨認出自己的同類
in a crowd.
顏色也可表明它是幼年還是成年
Color also indicates whether a fish is a juvenile or adult,
有些魚在性成熟時，顏色變化非常明顯
and some fish change color quite radically as they mature.
一旦魚兒成為配偶
Once fish are paired up,
它們用身體的姿態和顏色
they can then use body posturing and color displays
來傳達自己的意圖
to communicate their intentions.
雄鸚嘴魚豎起背鰭恐嚇其它雄性
A male parrotfish erects his dorsal fin to intimidate other males
給近旁那條模樣完全不同的雌魚留下好印象
and impress a nearby female who happens to look completely different.
珊瑚礁裡，魚兒都在尋找交配的機會
And all across the reef, fish are on the lookout for a chance to mate
以傳承它們寶貴的基因
and pass on their precious genes.
和人類相比，大多數海洋生物的一生短暫而緊張
Most sea creatures have short, intense lives compared to ours.
有些魚只有短短幾年壽命
For some fish, a few years constitutes an entire lifetime.
所以，珊瑚礁中的每一天都很重要
So every good day on a reef is truly great.
10年好時光就更棒了
A good decade is even greater,
這使無數海洋生物有機會
the chance for countless marine creatures
將它們的生命發揮到淋漓盡致
to live their lives to the fullest
並繁衍後代
and give rise to new generations.
要在熱帶海洋中生存
In the quest to survive in these tropical seas,
動物們必須極富創造性
animals have had to be highly inventive
有時還要打破自然規律
and sometimes nature's own rules are broken.
看看海馬
Consider the seahorse.
這些擁有各種尺寸的神秘生物
These mystical creatures come in all sizes.
有的比你的手掌還大，有的卻和你的指甲一樣小
Some bigger than your palm, others as small as your fingernail.
最小巧的是侏儒海馬
The daintiest of them all is the pygmy seahorse,
它們一輩子都綁在柳珊瑚上
whose life is completely bound to gorgonian coral.
海馬家族有320種
The extended seahorse family consists of 320 species,
包括海龍，海馬等
and includes pipefishes, pipehorses and sea dragons.
它們當中的大多數種類
In most species of pipefish and seahorse,
是由雄性養育後代
it's the male that broods the young.
這特殊的養育方式不是唯一使它們與眾不同的地方
It's not just this unusual parenting that sets them apart.
它們有像馬一樣的腦袋
They have equine heads,
捲曲的尾巴
prehensile tails...
有骨板而不是鱗片
..and bony body plates instead of scales.
儘管它們有龍一樣的外表，很多魚喜歡吃它們
Despite their dragon appearance, many fish like to eat them.
所以不被發現變成它們的特長
So not being noticed has become their speciality.
剃刀魚擅長偽裝成其它動植物
Ghost pipefish are expert mimics of other animals and plants,
包括海百合和珊瑚
including crinoids and coral.
它們的天敵很難發現它們
Their predators find it hard to see them
它們的食物也一樣
and so does their prey.
它們一生中大部分時間都是頭朝下
They spend most of their lives upside down,
專注於沙質海底
focused intently on the sandy bottom,
尋找小型甲殼動物
searching for the tiny crustaceans
這是它們的主要食物
that are their principal food.
而海龍的偽裝是如此特別
So specific is their camouflage
它們鮮少遠離其特定棲地
that pipefish rarely wander far from a particular habitat
同時完善它們的模仿細節
and perfect their mimicry down to the finest detail.
其他種類則是通過像漩渦
Other species conceal their true identity
和水流般運動來隱蹤匿跡
by moving like eddies and currents.
有的假裝是被沙包裹的木棍
While some pretend to be sand-encrusted sticks
或落葉
or fallen leaves...
或是一片海藻
..or pieces of algae.
如果你知道如何觀察，偽裝大師無處不在
If you know how to look, the masters of disguise are everywhere.
在這水下伊甸園
In this underwater Garden of Eden,
甚至看起來是蛇，其實也是魚而已
even the snake turns out to be a fish.
在海床上，欺騙屢見不鮮
Down on the seabed, deception is commonplace.
單個的珊瑚往往由沙礫區連接
Individual reefs are often connected by areas of sand and rubble,
這是所謂的「底棲地」
and this is where the so-called 'bottom dwellers' dwell.
這裡數量最多的是蝦虎魚
The most numerous of these are the gobies.
超過2000種蝦虎魚
There are over 2,000 species of goby,
使之成為最大的魚類家族之一
making them one of the largest fish families.
很少有能長到超過手指大小的
Few of them grow bigger than your finger,
這使它們成為許多掠食魚類的食物
which makes them a favored food for many large predatory fish.
所以它們很警惕，從不遠離海床
So they're always on the lookout and never far from the seabed.
它們大部分時間都用來覓食
They spend most of their days feeding,
用腮過濾沙子尋找食物微粒
filtering sand through their gills to extract tiny food particles.
對蝦虎魚來說，沙子就是一切
Sand is everything to the goby.
沙子提供食物
Sand puts food in their belly
和藏身地
and also a roof above their heads.
許多蝦虎魚建造洞穴
Many gobies build burrows.
這是辛苦的挖掘工作
Its tiring excavation work,
合作者們有時在該誰幹活的問題上不能達成一致
and partners sometimes don't agree on whose turn it is.
如果內部問題得不到解決
If the domestic argument can't be worked out,
這種偽裝成大眼睛的蝦虎魚
then this species, camouflaged as big eyes,
會出去閒逛一會兒把問題解決
can always go for a stroll to smooth things over.
有些聰明的蝦虎魚已經找到為之服務的奴隸了
Some clever gobies have enlisted the services of a slave.
在這個非凡的夥伴關係中
In a most extraordinary partnership,
蝦虎魚和盲蝦因相互需要而生活一起
gobies and blind shrimp live together, bonded by mutual need.
蝦虎魚藏身在盲蝦挖出的洞穴中
The shrimps excavate a burrow in which the gobies can hide,
蝦則吃它們的殘羹剩飯
and they eat the goby's scraps.
蝦虎魚負責放哨，警告靠近危險的蝦
The gobies act as sentinels, warning the shrimps of approaching danger.
魚和甲殼類動物有如此密切的工作關係
The fish and crustacea have such a close working relationship
它們總是通過尾部，鰭或觸角
that they're always connected,
相互聯繫
by tail or fin or feeler.
對於食物鏈底部的魚類
For fish close to the bottom of the food chain,
安全的家是至關重要的
a safe home base is essential.
空間有限，好的房地產可謂來之不易
Space is limited and good real estate hard to come by.
擅入領地是不能容忍的
Trespassing isn't tolerated.
領土爭端通常會被快速解決掉
Territorial disputes are normally quick to work out.
但也不盡然
But not always.
沒有必要和
There's definitely no point picking a fight
這強大的裝甲獸為敵
with this mighty armored beast.
棘冠海星是珊瑚的死敵
It's the crown-of-thorns starfish, corals' mortal enemy.
它們把胃吐出，並用胃酸覆蓋珊瑚蟲
By disgorging their stomachs and drenching polyps with acid,
它們吃活珊瑚，把珊瑚蟲從礁石裡吸食出來
they eat living coral and suck the life out of a reef.
海星在清潔空間和促進
The starfish play an important role,
生物多樣性方面扮演了重要角色
clearing space and fostering biodiversity.
很少有和它們同樣地位的生物
And few have stood in their way.
海星一直都是自然循環的一部分
The starfish have always been a natural part of the cycle.
但現在不那麼自然了
But now the cycle is unnatural.
農業污染增加了水中的營養
Agricultural pollution has increased nutrients in the water,
引發赤潮（藻華）
which in turn causes algal blooms.
幼體海星在享受海藻大餐
Starfish juveniles are feasting on this algae
同時越來越多的海星活到成年
and many more are surviving into adulthood.
現在棘冠海星的爆發定期出現在
Plagues of crown-of-thorns starfish are now regularly experienced
全世界的珊瑚礁中
on reefs worldwide.
但不是所有的都是壞消息
But not all infestations are bad news.
完美的例子就是有個不尋常的聯盟
A perfect example is the unlikely alliance
出現在耳海綿與粉海參之間
between the eared sponge and the pink sea cucumber.
這種海綿對大多數生物來說是劇毒的
This sponge is highly toxic to most.
但海參已經適應它，並在此大量聚居
But the sea cucumber has adapted to live here in huge numbers,
並跑到海綿邊緣產卵
rising off the edges to spawn.
這是一片生物蓬勃生長的不宜居住之地
This is an inhospitable habitat where creatures are thriving.
在不斷變化的海洋裡，這也許提供了生活的希望
Perhaps it offers hope for life in our changing seas.
這是萬事皆有可能的絕佳佐證
It's certainly proof that anything is possible.
海洋世界永遠在變化
The oceanic world is ever changing.
沒有什麼是一成不變的
Nothing stays the same here for more than a moment.
歷史上，珊瑚總是來來去去
Over the ages, corals have come and gone.
今天，它們正在再次消失
Today, they are disappearing again.
但正是人類的存在，使它不同於
But what sets this cycle apart from any other in geological history
地質史上的其他幾次循環
is the presence of us.
珊瑚的生存史上，這是第一次
For the first time in corals' existence,
人類直接影響海洋的化學成分
humans are having a direct impact on the ocean's chemistry
和珊瑚的命運
and corals' destiny.
許多科學家認為
Many scientists believe
我們正面臨下一個大滅絕
we are heading towards our next mass extinction
而且人類就是罪魁禍首
and that humans are the cause.
造礁珊瑚已嚴重瀕危
Reef-building corals are now seriously endangered.
當珊瑚礁消失時
And as reefs disappear,
眾多依賴它們的生物也會隨之消失
hundreds of thousands of dependent creatures disappear with them.
此外，珊瑚礁的消亡是海洋死亡的
Furthermore, the demise of coral reefs is a clear indicator
明確指示
that our ocean is dying,
海洋是地球的生命支持系統
and our ocean is our planet's life-support system.
拯救海洋的唯一方法就是
The only way to save our ocean
在未來一二十年內
is to radically curb our CO2 emissions
從根本上遏制二氧化碳的排放量
within the next one or two decades.
我們有實現這個目標的所有工具
We have all the tools to do it.
如果我們成功了，將不僅拯救珊瑚礁
And if we succeed, we will not only save our reefs,
最終還會拯救我們自己
we will ultimately save ourselves.
珊瑚的未來，珊瑚的故事如何結束
The future of coral, and how this story ends,
都取決於我們
is up to us.